A Guide to the University of Virginia World War II Records,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
University of Virginia World War II Records
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/3.061
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records pertaining to the participation of the University of Virginia in World War II consist of several collections, formerly with manuscript accession numbers, including the following:
2153 Gift of Joseph L. Vaughan, School of Engineering, UVA, on April 13, 1945.
2185 Gift of James Hart, Colonnade Club, UVA, on May 22, 1945.
2192 Gift of Captain Moomaw, Headquarters, 3317th Service Unit, UVA, on June 22,1945.
2193 Gift of Dr. Harvey E. Jordan, University Hospital, UVA, on June 22, 1945.
2293 Gift of Joseph L. Vaughan, School of Engineering, UVA, on May 14, 1946.
2302 Gift of President's Office, University of Virginia, on May 21, 1946.
2333 U.S. Navy to UVA President's Office, then archival transfer on June 19, 1946.
2366 Gift of Isabella Burnet, Charlottesville, on August 20, 1945.
2368 Gift of Joseph L. Vaughan, School of Engineering, UVA, on August 20, 1945.
2497 Gift of Professor William A. Kepner, Biology, UVA, on September 6, 1946.
7619 Archival transfer on July 12, 1964.
7619-a Anonymous gift on August 29, 1964.
8957 Archival transfer on August 15, 1968.
8980 Anonymous gift on August 29, 1968.
9072 Archival transfer on December 27, 1968.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the records of the University of Virginia and its participation in World War II, 1938-1946, 1951, and undated, ca. 1,650 items (7 Hollinger boxes, 3 linear feet), chiefly correspondence; applications, course outlines, instructor's notes, student papers, course work, examinations and grades; financial material, such as invoices; photographs; and historical material and speeches about World War II.
Correspondence in the collection include: cards and letters to Professor Joseph L. Vaughan from former students in the University of Virginia Engineering School and other alumni in the services; correspondence from Lewis Goldstein to William Kepner; correspondence of the 8th Evacuation Hospital Unit; and correspondence of B.F.D. Runk and Tom Brown.
Materials concerned with the history of University involvement in World War II, include the papers of the University of Virginia Committee on the Preservation of Material on World War II, 1941-1946; Address cards for Medical Alumni in Service; a history of the 3317th Army Specialized Training Unit; the remarks of James Hart on V-E Day; and Lamont Pugh's speech to the Medical Alumni, And So It Rolls.
Arrangement
This collection consists of three series. Series I: Army Air Force Pre-Meteorological Program (Boxes 1-5). Series II: General and Navy Files (Boxes 5-7). Series III: World War II History Commission (Box 7)
Contents List
- Series I: Army Air Force Pre-Meteorological Program
  - Pre-Meteorological Program-Charles H. Kauffmann, 1942 December-1943 March (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Pre-Meteorological Program-Gordon Whyburn, 1943 February-1944 January (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence: George O. Ferguson and Captain Clifford Rawson, 1943 February-March (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence: Grade Requests, 1943 June-1945 June (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence: Charles H. Kauffmann- Application Information A-D, 1942 December-1943 April (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence: Charles H. Kauffmann-Application Information E-L, 1942 December-1943 April (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence: Charles H. Kauffmann-Application Information M-S, 1942 December-1943 May (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence: Charles H. Kauffmann-Application Information T-Z, 1942 December-1943 April (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence: Position Inquires, 1943 March-June (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn, 1943 February-1944 June (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn and H.R. Byers, Institute of Meteorology, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn and William L. Hart, Consultant Army Air Forces, 1943 February- April (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn and Eldon L. Johnson, Academic Director, 1943 March-1944 February (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn and Major H.E. Knierim, Charlottesville Training Detachment, 1943 February-May (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn and William T. Reid, Acting Academic Director, 1944 March (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn and C.G. Rossby, Chairman of University Meteorological Committee, 1943 February-1944 April (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Correspondence: Gordon Whyburn and Major Darius D. Thorpe, Charlottesville Training Detachment, 1943 June-1944 February (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Course Outlines: Courses I-III, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Course Outlines: Courses IV- V, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Course V Examinations, 1943 June-1944 January (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Course V Instructors' Notes, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Course V Instructors' Record Books, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Course V Student Papers C-J, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Course V Student Papers N-T, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Faculty Lists, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Grades, 1944 February (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Grades, 1944 January (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Grades, 1943 November, December (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Grades, 1943 September, October (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Grades, 1943 August (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Grades, 1943 June, July (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Grades, 1943 May (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Grades, 1943 March, April (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Graduation Information, 1944 February (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Invoices for Textbooks and Supplies, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Pamphlets and Information, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 5:2)
- Series II: General and Navy Files
  - Civil Defense Organization, 1942 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Correspondence: from China, 1938 November-1944 September (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Correspondence: Eighth Evacuation Hospital, 1943 March-1945 October (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Correspondence: Lewis Goldstein to William A. Kepner, 1944 September-1945 January (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Correspondence: Alumni in Service to Professors, 1941 December-1945 February (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Correspondence: Lt. Comm. B.F.D. Runk and Lt. Tom Brown to Professors, 1944 April-1945 May (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Correspondence: Alumni A-K to Joseph L. Vaughan, 1944 February-1946 June (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Correspondence: Alumni L-W to Joseph L. Vaughan, 1943 January-1945 December (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Correspondence: Joseph L. Vaughan Newsletters to Alumni, 1945 January-August (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Extension Division Reports, 1943 February-1944 June (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Extension Division Reports, 1941 June-1942 October (Box-folder 6:2)
  - History of the 3317th Army Specialized Training Unit at University of Virginia, n.d. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Medical Alumni in Service Address Cards A-N, n.d. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Medical Alumni in Service Address Cards O-Y, n.d. (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Members of Geology B-1 Class Killed in WWII (1926-1945), [1945] (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Minute Men of '40, 1940 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Naval Building Ground Breaking Photo of President Newcomb, University physicists, and Naval Officers, 1946 May (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Naval Marchk of Commendation, V-12 Unit, 1946 June (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Naval Ordinance Development Award for Guided Missile and Pin, 1945 December (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps, 1942 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Naval ROTC Placard concerning Sign-out for meals to be missed, [1943 August 30], Oversize.
  - Navy V-12 Training Unit, 1943 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Fifth Naval District war diary of Captain Edgar M. Williams 1944 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Photographs: Dawn Patrol,n.d. (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Photographs: General Activities, [1942] (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Photographs: Third War Loan, University of Virginia, 1943 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Photograph: University of Virginia Corps of Cadets 1941 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Purdue University Preservation Pamphlets, 1942, 1944 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Rural Social Economics Alumni Newsletter, 1943 September-1945 July (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Speech by James Hart on V-E Day, 1945 May 8 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Speech by Lamont Pugh, Rear Admirable Surgeon General of the Navy, And So It Rolls,1951 June 8 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Street Map of Bombay, India, n.d. (Box-folder 7:10)
  - Requests for Recommendations and Commissions, etc. sent to Gordon Whyburn, 1942 January-1944 January (Box-folder 7:11)
  - Red Cross Certificate to Roy Land, n.d. (Box-folder 7:12)
- Series III: World War II History Commission
  - Replies to Circular Letter to Deans about UVA during World War II, 1944 February-July (Box-folder 7:13)
  - Replies to Circular Letter to Professors about Work during World War II, 1943 September-1944 April (Box-folder 7:14)
  - University of Virginia Committee on the Preservation of Material on World War II, 1941-1944 July (Box-folder 7:15)
  - University of Virginia in World War II, Jane Carson, 1944 (Box-folder 7:16)
  - Virginia World War II History Commission, 1945 April-1948 June (Box-folder 7:17)